<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version="2.0">
  <head>
    <title></title>
    <dateModified></dateModified>
    <ownerName></ownerName>
  </head>
  <body>
<outline text="The Economy of Ideas | &lt;em&gt;WIRED&lt;/em&gt;">
  <outline text="A framework for patents and copyrights in the Digital Age. (Everything you know about intellectual property is wrong.)">
    <outline text="John Perry Barlow">
    </outline>
    <outline text="March 1994" _note="&gt; &quot;If nature has made any one thing less susceptible than all others of&#10;&gt; exclusive property, it is the action of the thinking power called an&#10;&gt; idea, which an individual may exclusively possess as long as he keeps&#10;&gt; it to himself; but the moment it is divulged, it forces itself into&#10;&gt; the possession of everyone, and the receiver cannot dispossess himself&#10;&gt; of it. Its peculiar character, too, is that no one possesses the less,&#10;&gt; because every other possesses the whole of it. He who receives an idea&#10;&gt; from me, receives instruction himself without lessening mine; as he&#10;&gt; who lights his taper at mine, receives light without darkening me.&#10;&gt; That ideas should freely spread from one to another over the globe,&#10;&gt; for the moral and mutual instruction of man, and improvement of his&#10;&gt; condition, seems to have been peculiarly and benevolently designed by&#10;&gt; nature, when she made them, like fire, expansible over all space,&#10;&gt; without lessening their density at any point, and like the air in&#10;&gt; which we breathe, move, and have our physical being, incapable of&#10;&gt; confinement or exclusive appropriation. Inventions then cannot, in&#10;&gt; nature, be a subject of property.&quot; - Thomas Jefferson&#10;&#10;------------------------------------------------------------------------&#10;&#10;Throughout the time I've been groping around cyberspace, an immense,&#10;unsolved conundrum has remained at the root of nearly every legal,&#10;ethical, governmental, and social vexation to be found in the Virtual&#10;World. I refer to the problem of digitized property. The enigma is this:&#10;If our property can be infinitely reproduced and instantaneously&#10;distributed all over the planet without cost, without our knowledge,&#10;without its even leaving our possession, how can we protect it? How are&#10;we going to get paid for the work we do with our minds? And, if we can't&#10;get paid, what will assure the continued creation and distribution of&#10;such work?&#10;&#10;Since we don't have a solution to what is a profoundly new kind of&#10;challenge, and are apparently unable to delay the galloping digitization&#10;of everything not obstinately physical, we are sailing into the future&#10;on a sinking ship.&#10;&#10;This vessel, the accumulated canon of copyright and patent law, was&#10;developed to convey forms and methods of expression entirely different&#10;from the vaporous cargo it is now being asked to carry. It is leaking as&#10;much from within as from without.&#10;&#10;Legal efforts to keep the old boat floating are taking three forms: a&#10;frenzy of deck chair rearrangement, stern warnings to the passengers&#10;that if she goes down, they will face harsh criminal penalties, and&#10;serene, glassy-eyed denial.&#10;&#10;Intellectual property law cannot be patched, retrofitted, or expanded to&#10;contain digitized expression any more than real estate law might be&#10;revised to cover the allocation of broadcasting spectrum (which, in&#10;fact, rather resembles what is being attempted here). We will need to&#10;develop an entirely new set of methods as befits this entirely new set&#10;of circumstances.&#10;&#10;Most of the people who actually create soft property - the programmers,&#10;hackers, and Net surfers - already know this. Unfortunately, neither the&#10;companies they work for nor the lawyers these companies hire have enough&#10;direct experience with nonmaterial goods to understand why they are so&#10;problematic. They are proceeding as though the old laws can somehow be&#10;made to work, either by grotesque expansion or by force. They are wrong.&#10;&#10;The source of this conundrum is as simple as its solution is complex.&#10;Digital technology is detaching information from the physical plane,&#10;where property law of all sorts has always found definition.&#10;&#10;Throughout the history of copyrights and patents, the proprietary&#10;assertions of thinkers have been focused not on their ideas but on the&#10;expression of those ideas. The ideas themselves, as well as facts about&#10;the phenomena of the world, were considered to be the collective&#10;property of humanity. One could claim franchise, in the case of&#10;copyright, on the precise turn of phrase used to convey a particular&#10;idea or the order in which facts were presented.&#10;&#10;The point at which this franchise was imposed was that moment when the&#10;&quot;word became flesh&quot; by departing the mind of its originator and entering&#10;some physical object, whether book or widget. The subsequent arrival of&#10;other commercial media besides books didn't alter the legal importance&#10;of this moment. Law protected expression and, with few (and recent)&#10;exceptions, to express was to make physical.&#10;&#10;Protecting physical expression had the force of convenience on its side.&#10;Copyright worked well because, Gutenberg notwithstanding, it was hard to&#10;make a book. Furthermore, books froze their contents into a condition&#10;which was as challenging to alter as it was to reproduce. Counterfeiting&#10;and distributing counterfeit volumes were obvious and visible activities&#10;- it was easy enough to catch somebody in the act of doing. Finally,&#10;unlike unbounded words or images, books had material surfaces to which&#10;one could attach copyright notices, publisher's marques, and price tags.&#10;&#10;Mental-to-physical conversion was even more central to patent. A patent,&#10;until recently, was either a description of the form into which&#10;materials were to be rendered in the service of some purpose, or a&#10;description of the process by which rendition occurred. In either case,&#10;the conceptual heart of patent was the material result. If no purposeful&#10;object could be rendered because of some material limitation, the patent&#10;was rejected. Neither a Klein bottle nor a shovel made of silk could be&#10;patented. It had to be a thing, and the thing had to work.&#10;&#10;Thus, the rights of invention and authorship adhered to activities in&#10;the physical world. One didn't get paid for ideas, but for the ability&#10;to deliver them into reality. For all practical purposes, the value was&#10;in the conveyance and not in the thought conveyed.&#10;&#10;In other words, the bottle was protected, not the wine.&#10;&#10;Now, as information enters cyberspace, the native home of Mind, these&#10;bottles are vanishing. With the advent of digitization, it is now&#10;possible to replace all previous information storage forms with one&#10;metabottle: complex and highly liquid patterns of ones and zeros.&#10;&#10;Even the physical/digital bottles to which we've become accustomed -&#10;floppy disks, CD-ROMs, and other discrete, shrink-wrappable bit-packages&#10;- will disappear as all computers jack-in to the global Net. While the&#10;Internet may never include every CPU on the planet, it is more than&#10;doubling every year and can be expected to become the principal medium&#10;of information conveyance, and perhaps eventually, the only one.&#10;&#10;Once that has happened, all the goods of the Information Age - all of&#10;the expressions once contained in books or film strips or newsletters -&#10;will exist either as pure thought or something very much like thought:&#10;voltage conditions darting around the Net at the speed of light, in&#10;conditions that one might behold in effect, as glowing pixels or&#10;transmitted sounds, but never touch or claim to &quot;own&quot; in the old sense&#10;of the word.&#10;&#10;Some might argue that information will still require some physical&#10;manifestation, such as its magnetic existence on the titanic hard disks&#10;of distant servers, but these are bottles which have no macroscopically&#10;discrete or personally meaningful form.&#10;&#10;Some will also argue that we have been dealing with unbottled expression&#10;since the advent of radio, and they would be right. But for most of the&#10;history of broadcast, there was no convenient way to capture soft goods&#10;from the electromagnetic ether and reproduce them with quality available&#10;in commercial packages. Only recently has this changed, and little has&#10;been done legally or technically to address the change.&#10;&#10;Generally, the issue of consumer payment for broadcast products was&#10;irrelevant. The consumers themselves were the product. Broadcast media&#10;were supported either by the sale of the attention of their audience to&#10;advertisers, by government assessing payment through taxes, or by the&#10;whining mendicancy of annual donor drives.&#10;&#10;All of the broadcast-support models are flawed. Support either by&#10;advertisers or government has almost invariably tainted the purity of&#10;the goods delivered. Besides, direct marketing is gradually killing the&#10;advertiser-support model anyway.&#10;&#10;Broadcast media gave us another payment method for a virtual product:&#10;the royalties that broadcasters pay songwriters through such&#10;organizations as ASCAP and BMI. But, as a member of ASCAP, I can assure&#10;you this is not a model that we should emulate. The monitoring methods&#10;are wildly approximate. There is no parallel system of accounting in the&#10;revenue stream. It doesn't really work. Honest.&#10;&#10;In any case, without our old methods, based on physically defining the&#10;expression of ideas, and in the absence of successful new models for&#10;nonphysical transaction, we simply don't know how to assure reliable&#10;payment for mental works. To make matters worse, this comes at a time&#10;when the human mind is replacing sunlight and mineral deposits as the&#10;principal source of new wealth.&#10;&#10;Furthermore, the increasing difficulty of enforcing existing copyright&#10;and patent laws is already placing in peril the ultimate source of&#10;intellectual property - the free exchange of ideas.&#10;&#10;That is, when the primary articles of commerce in a society look so much&#10;like speech as to be indistinguishable from it, and when the traditional&#10;methods of protecting their ownership have become ineffectual,&#10;attempting to fix the problem with broader and more vigorous enforcement&#10;will inevitably threaten freedom of speech. The greatest constraint on&#10;your future liberties may come not from government but from corporate&#10;legal departments laboring to protect by force what can no longer be&#10;protected by practical efficiency or general social consent.&#10;&#10;Furthermore, when Jefferson and his fellow creatures of the&#10;Enlightenment designed the system that became American copyright law,&#10;their primary objective was assuring the widespread distribution of&#10;thought, not profit. Profit was the fuel that would carry ideas into the&#10;libraries and minds of their new republic. Libraries would purchase&#10;books, thus rewarding the authors for their work in assembling ideas;&#10;these ideas, otherwise &quot;incapable of confinement,&quot; would then become&#10;freely available to the public. But what is the role of libraries in the&#10;absence of books? How does society now pay for the distribution of ideas&#10;if not by charging for the ideas themselves?&#10;&#10;Additionally complicating the matter is the fact that along with the&#10;disappearance of the physical bottles in which intellectual property&#10;protection has resided, digital technology is also erasing the legal&#10;jurisdictions of the physical world and replacing them with the&#10;unbounded and perhaps permanently lawless waves of cyberspace.&#10;&#10;In cyberspace, no national or local boundaries contain the scene of a&#10;crime and determine the method of its prosecution; worse, no clear&#10;cultural agreements define what a crime might be. Unresolved and basic&#10;differences between Western and Asian cultural assumptions about&#10;intellectual property can only be exacerbated when many transactions are&#10;taking place in both hemispheres and yet, somehow, in neither.&#10;&#10;Even in the most local of digital conditions, jurisdiction and&#10;responsibility are hard to assess. A group of music publishers filed&#10;suit against CompuServe this fall because it allowed its users to upload&#10;musical compositions into areas where other users might access them. But&#10;since CompuServe cannot practically exercise much control over the flood&#10;of bits that passes between its subscribers, it probably shouldn't be&#10;held responsible for unlawfully &quot;publishing&quot; these works.&#10;&#10;Notions of property, value, ownership, and the nature of wealth itself&#10;are changing more fundamentally than at any time since the Sumerians&#10;first poked cuneiform into wet clay and called it stored grain. Only a&#10;very few people are aware of the enormity of this shift, and fewer of&#10;them are lawyers or public officials.&#10;&#10;Those who do see these changes must prepare responses for the legal and&#10;social confusion that will erupt as efforts to protect new forms of&#10;property with old methods become more obviously futile, and, as a&#10;consequence, more adamant.">
    </outline>
  </outline>
  <outline text="From Swords to Writs to Bits" _note="Humanity now seems bent on creating a world economy primarily based on&#10;goods that take no material form. In doing so, we may be eliminating any&#10;predictable connection between creators and a fair reward for the&#10;utility or pleasure others may find in their works.&#10;&#10;Without that connection, and without a fundamental change in&#10;consciousness to accommodate its loss, we are building our future on&#10;furor, litigation, and institutionalized evasion of payment except in&#10;response to raw force. We may return to the Bad Old Days of property.&#10;&#10;Throughout the darker parts of human history, the possession and&#10;distribution of property was a largely military matter. &quot;Ownership&quot; was&#10;assured those with the nastiest tools, whether fists or armies, and the&#10;most resolute will to use them. Property was the divine right of thugs.&#10;&#10;By the turn of the First Millennium AD, the emergence of merchant&#10;classes and landed gentry forced the development of ethical&#10;understandings for the resolution of property disputes. In the Middle&#10;Ages, enlightened rulers like England's Henry II began to codify this&#10;unwritten &quot;common law&quot; into recorded canons. These laws were local,&#10;which didn't matter much as they were primarily directed at real estate,&#10;a form of property that is local by definition. And, as the name&#10;implied, was very real.&#10;&#10;This continued to be the case as long as the origin of wealth was&#10;agricultural, but with that dawning of the Industrial Revolution,&#10;humanity began to focus as much on means as ends. Tools acquired a new&#10;social value and, thanks to their development, it became possible to&#10;duplicate and distribute them in quantity.&#10;&#10;To encourage their invention, copyright and patent law were developed in&#10;most Western countries. These laws were devoted to the delicate task of&#10;getting mental creations into the world where they could be used - and&#10;could enter the minds of others - while assuring their inventors&#10;compensation for the value of their use. And, as previously stated, the&#10;systems of both law and practice which grew up around that task were&#10;based on physical expression.&#10;&#10;Since it is now possible to convey ideas from one mind to another&#10;without ever making them physical, we are now claiming to own ideas&#10;themselves and not merely their expression. And since it is likewise now&#10;possible to create useful tools that never take physical form, we have&#10;taken to patenting abstractions, sequences of virtual events, and&#10;mathematical formulae - the most unreal estate imaginable.&#10;&#10;In certain areas, this leaves rights of ownership in such an ambiguous&#10;condition that property again adheres to those who can muster the&#10;largest armies. The only difference is that this time the armies consist&#10;of lawyers.&#10;&#10;Threatening their opponents with the endless purgatory of litigation,&#10;over which some might prefer death itself, they assert claim to any&#10;thought which might have entered another cranium within the collective&#10;body of the corporations they serve. They act as though these ideas&#10;appeared in splendid detachment from all previous human thought. And&#10;they pretend that thinking about a product is somehow as good as&#10;manufacturing, distributing, and selling it.&#10;&#10;What was previously considered a common human resource, distributed&#10;among the minds and libraries of the world, as well as the phenomena of&#10;nature herself, is now being fenced and deeded. It is as though a new&#10;class of enterprise had arisen that claimed to own the air.&#10;&#10;What is to be done? While there is a certain grim fun to be had in it,&#10;dancing on the grave of copyright and patent will solve little,&#10;especially when so few are willing to admit that the occupant of this&#10;grave is even deceased, and so many are trying to uphold by force what&#10;can no longer be upheld by popular consent.&#10;&#10;The legalists, desperate over their slipping grip, are vigorously trying&#10;to extend their reach. Indeed, the United States and other proponents of&#10;GATT are making adherence to our moribund systems of intellectual&#10;property protection a condition of membership in the marketplace of&#10;nations. For example, China will be denied Most Favored Nation trading&#10;status unless they agree to uphold a set of culturally alien principles&#10;that are no longer even sensibly applicable in their country of origin.&#10;&#10;In a more perfect world, we'd be wise to declare a moratorium on&#10;litigation, legislation, and international treaties in this area until&#10;we had a clearer sense of the terms and conditions of enterprise in&#10;cyberspace. Ideally, laws ratify already developed social consensus.&#10;They are less the Social Contract itself than a series of memoranda&#10;expressing a collective intent that has emerged out of many millions of&#10;human interactions.&#10;&#10;Humans have not inhabited cyberspace long enough or in sufficient&#10;diversity to have developed a Social Contract which conforms to the&#10;strange new conditions of that world. Laws developed prior to consensus&#10;usually favor the already established few who can get them passed and&#10;not society as a whole.&#10;&#10;To the extent that law and established social practice exists in this&#10;area, they are already in dangerous disagreement. The laws regarding&#10;unlicensed reproduction of commercial software are clear and stern...and&#10;rarely observed. Software piracy laws are so practically unenforceable&#10;and breaking them has become so socially acceptable that only a thin&#10;minority appears compelled, either by fear or conscience, to obey them.&#10;When I give speeches on this subject, I always ask how many people in&#10;the audience can honestly claim to have no unauthorized software on&#10;their hard disks. I've never seen more than 10 percent of the hands go&#10;up.&#10;&#10;Whenever there is such profound divergence between law and social&#10;practice, it is not society that adapts. Against the swift tide of&#10;custom, the software publishers' current practice of hanging a few&#10;visible scapegoats is so obviously capricious as to only further&#10;diminish respect for the law.&#10;&#10;Part of the widespread disregard for commercial software copyrights&#10;stems from a legislative failure to understand the conditions into which&#10;it was inserted. To assume that systems of law based in the physical&#10;world will serve in an environment as fundamentally different as&#10;cyberspace is a folly for which everyone doing business in the future&#10;will pay.&#10;&#10;As I will soon discuss in detail, unbounded intellectual property is&#10;very different from physical property and can no longer be protected as&#10;though these differences did not exist. For example, if we continue to&#10;assume that value is based on scarcity, as it is with regard to physical&#10;objects, we will create laws that are precisely contrary to the nature&#10;of information, which may, in many cases, increase in value with&#10;distribution.&#10;&#10;The large, legally risk-averse institutions most likely to play by the&#10;old rules will suffer for their compliance. As more lawyers, guns, and&#10;money are invested in either protecting their rights or subverting those&#10;of their opponents, their ability to produce new technology will simply&#10;grind to a halt as every move they make drives them deeper into a tar&#10;pit of courtroom warfare.&#10;&#10;Faith in law will not be an effective strategy for high-tech companies.&#10;Law adapts by continuous increments and at a pace second only to&#10;geology. Technology advances in lunging jerks, like the punctuation of&#10;biological evolution grotesquely accelerated. Real-world conditions will&#10;continue to change at a blinding pace, and the law will lag further&#10;behind, more profoundly confused. This mismatch may prove impossible to&#10;overcome.&#10;&#10;Promising economies based on purely digital products will either be born&#10;in a state of paralysis, as appears to be the case with multimedia, or&#10;continue in a brave and willful refusal by their owners to play the&#10;ownership game at all.&#10;&#10;In the United States one can already see a parallel economy developing,&#10;mostly among small, fast moving enterprises who protect their ideas by&#10;getting into the marketplace quicker then their larger competitors who&#10;base their protection on fear and litigation.&#10;&#10;Perhaps those who are part of the problem will simply quarantine&#10;themselves in court, while those who are part of the solution will&#10;create a new society based, at first, on piracy and freebooting. It may&#10;well be that when the current system of intellectual property law has&#10;collapsed, as seems inevitable, that no new legal structure will arise&#10;in its place.&#10;&#10;But something will happen. After all, people do business. When a&#10;currency becomes meaningless, business is done in barter. When societies&#10;develop outside the law, they develop their own unwritten codes,&#10;practices, and ethical systems. While technology may undo law,&#10;technology offers methods for restoring creative rights.&#10;&#10;**A Taxonomy of Information**&#10;&#10;It seems to me that the most productive thing to do now is to look into&#10;the true nature of what we're trying to protect. How much do we really&#10;know about information and its natural behaviors?&#10;&#10;What are the essential characteristics of unbounded creation? How does&#10;it differ from previous forms of property? How many of our assumptions&#10;about it have actually been about its containers rather than their&#10;mysterious contents? What are its different species and how does each of&#10;them lend itself to control? What technologies will be useful in&#10;creating new virtual bottles to replace the old physical ones?&#10;&#10;Of course, information is, by nature, intangible and hard to define.&#10;Like other such deep phenomena as light or matter, it is a natural host&#10;to paradox. It is most helpful to understand light as being both a&#10;particle and a wave, an understanding of information may emerge in the&#10;abstract congruence of its several different properties which might be&#10;described by the following three statements:&#10;&#10;Information is an activity.  &#10;Information is a life form.  &#10;Information is a relationship.&#10;&#10;In the following section, I will examine each of these.">
  </outline>
  <outline text="I. INFORMATION IS AN ACTIVITY">
    <outline text="Information Is a Verb, Not a Noun." _note="Freed of its containers, information is obviously not a thing. In fact,&#10;it is something that happens in the field of interaction between minds&#10;or objects or other pieces of information.&#10;&#10;Gregory Bateson, expanding on the information theory of Claude Shannon,&#10;said, &quot;Information is a difference which makes a difference.&quot; Thus,&#10;information only really exists in the Delta. The making of that&#10;difference is an activity within a relationship. Information is an&#10;action which occupies time rather than a state of being which occupies&#10;physical space, as is the case with hard goods. It is the pitch, not the&#10;baseball, the dance, not the dancer.">
    </outline>
    <outline text="Information Is Experienced, Not Possessed." _note="Even when it has been encapsulated in some static form like a book or a&#10;hard disk, information is still something that happens to you as you&#10;mentally decompress it from its storage code. But, whether it's running&#10;at gigabits per second or words per minute, the actual decoding is a&#10;process that must be performed by and upon a mind, a process that must&#10;take place in time.&#10;&#10;There was a cartoon in the Bulletin of Atomic Scientists a few years ago&#10;that illustrated this point beautifully. In the drawing, a holdup man&#10;trains his gun on the sort of bespectacled fellow you'd figure might&#10;have a lot of information stored in his head. &quot;Quick,&quot; orders the&#10;bandit, &quot;give me all your ideas.&quot;&#10;&#10;**Information Has to Move.**&#10;&#10;Sharks are said to die of suffocation if they stop swimming, and the&#10;same is nearly true of information. Information that isn't moving ceases&#10;to exist as anything but potential...at least until it is allowed to&#10;move again. For this reason, the practice of information hoarding,&#10;common in bureaucracies, is an especially wrong-headed artifact of&#10;physically based value systems.&#10;&#10;**Information Is Conveyed by Propagation, Not Distribution.**&#10;&#10;The way in which information spreads is also very different from the&#10;distribution of physical goods. It moves more like something from nature&#10;than from a factory. It can concatenate like falling dominos or grow in&#10;the usual fractal lattice, like frost spreading on a window, but it&#10;cannot be shipped around like widgets, except to the extent that it can&#10;be contained in them. It doesn't simply move on; it leaves a trail&#10;everywhere it's been.&#10;&#10;The central economic distinction between information and physical&#10;property is that information can be transferred without leaving the&#10;possession of the original owner. If I sell you my horse, I can't ride&#10;him after that. If I sell you what I know, we both know it.">
    </outline>
  </outline>
  <outline text="II. INFORMATION IS A LIFE FORM">
    <outline text="Information Wants to Be Free." _note="Stewart Brand is generally credited with this elegant statement of the&#10;obvious, which recognizes both the natural desire of secrets to be told&#10;and the fact that they might be capable of possessing something like a&#10;&quot;desire&quot; in the first place.&#10;&#10;English biologist and philosopher Richard Dawkins proposed the idea of&#10;&quot;memes,&quot; self-replicating patterns of information that propagate&#10;themselves across the ecologies of mind, a pattern of reproduction much&#10;like that of life forms.&#10;&#10;I believe they are life forms in every respect but their freedom from&#10;the carbon atom. They self-reproduce, they interact with their&#10;surroundings and adapt to them, they mutate, they persist. They evolve&#10;to fill the empty niches of their local environments, which are, in this&#10;case the surrounding belief systems and cultures of their hosts, namely,&#10;us.&#10;&#10;Indeed, sociobiologists like Dawkins make a plausible case that&#10;carbon-based life forms are information as well, that, as the chicken is&#10;an egg's way of making another egg, the entire biological spectacle is&#10;just the DNA molecule's means of copying out more information strings&#10;exactly like itself.">
    </outline>
    <outline text="Information Replicates into the Cracks of Possibility." _note="Like DNA helices, ideas are relentless expansionists, always seeking new&#10;opportunities for Lebensraum. And, as in carbon-based nature, the more&#10;robust organisms are extremely adept at finding new places to live.&#10;Thus, just as the common housefly has insinuated itself into practically&#10;every ecosystem on the planet, so has the meme of &quot;life after death&quot;&#10;found a niche in most minds, or psycho-ecologies.&#10;&#10;The more universally resonant an idea or image or song , the more minds&#10;it will enter and remain within. Trying to stop the spread of a really&#10;robust piece of information is about as easy as keeping killer bees&#10;south of the border.">
    </outline>
    <outline text="Information Wants to Change." _note="If ideas and other interactive patterns of information are indeed life&#10;forms, they can be expected to evolve constantly into forms which will&#10;be more perfectly adapted to their surroundings. And, as we see, they&#10;are doing this all the time.&#10;&#10;But for a long time, our static media, whether carvings in stone, ink on&#10;paper, or dye on celluloid, have strongly resisted the evolutionary&#10;impulse, exalting as a consequence the author's ability to determine the&#10;finished product. But, as in an oral tradition, digitized information&#10;has no &quot;final cut.&quot;&#10;&#10;Digital information, unconstrained by packaging, is a continuing process&#10;more like the metamorphosing tales of prehistory than anything that will&#10;fit in shrink-wrap. From the Neolithic to Gutenberg (monks aside),&#10;information was passed on, mouth to ear, changing with every retelling&#10;(or resinging). The stories which once shaped our sense of the world&#10;didn't have authoritative versions. They adapted to each culture in&#10;which they found themselves being told.&#10;&#10;Because there was never a moment when the story was frozen in print, the&#10;so-called &quot;moral&quot; right of storytellers to own the tale was neither&#10;protected nor recognized. The story simply passed through each of them&#10;on its way to the next, where it would assume a different form. As we&#10;return to continuous information, we can expect the importance of&#10;authorship to diminish. Creative people may have to renew their&#10;acquaintance with humility.&#10;&#10;But our system of copyright makes no accommodation whatever for&#10;expressions which don't become fixed at some point nor for cultural&#10;expressions which lack a specific author or inventor.&#10;&#10;Jazz improvisations, stand-up comedy routines, mime performances,&#10;developing monologues, and unrecorded broadcast transmissions all lack&#10;the Constitutional requirement of fixation as a &quot;writing.&quot; Without being&#10;fixed by a point of publication the liquid works of the future will all&#10;look more like these continuously adapting and changing forms and will&#10;therefore exist beyond the reach of copyright.&#10;&#10;Copyright expert Pamela Samuelson tells of having attended a conference&#10;last year convened around the fact that Western countries may legally&#10;appropriate the music, designs, and biomedical lore of aboriginal people&#10;without compensation to their tribes of origin since those tribes are&#10;not an &quot;author&quot; or &quot;inventors.&quot;&#10;&#10;But soon most information will be generated collaboratively by the&#10;cyber-tribal hunter-gatherers of cyberspace. Our arrogant legal&#10;dismissal of the rights of &quot;primitives&quot; will be soon return to haunt us.">
    </outline>
    <outline text="Information Is Perishable." _note="With the exception of the rare classic, most information is like farm&#10;produce. Its quality degrades rapidly both over time and in distance&#10;from the source of production. But even here, value is highly subjective&#10;and conditional. Yesterday's papers are quite valuable to the historian.&#10;In fact, the older they are, the more valuable they become. On the other&#10;hand, a commodities broker might consider news of an event that occurred&#10;more than an hour ago to have lost any relevance.">
    </outline>
  </outline>
  <outline text="III. INFORMATION IS A RELATIONSHIP">
    <outline text="Meaning Has Value and Is Unique to Each Case." _note="In most cases, we assign value to information based on its&#10;meaningfulness. The place where information dwells, the holy moment&#10;where transmission becomes reception, is a region which has many&#10;shifting characteristics and flavors depending on the relationship of&#10;sender and receiver, the depth of their interactivity.&#10;&#10;Each such relationship is unique. Even in cases where the sender is a&#10;broadcast medium, and no response is returned, the receiver is hardly&#10;passive. Receiving information is often as creative an act as generating&#10;it.&#10;&#10;The value of what is sent depends entirely on the extent to which each&#10;individual receiver has the receptors - shared terminology, attention,&#10;interest, language, paradigm - necessary to render what is received&#10;meaningful.&#10;&#10;Understanding is a critical element increasingly overlooked in the&#10;effort to turn information into a commodity. Data may be any set of&#10;facts, useful or not, intelligible or inscrutable, germane or&#10;irrelevant. Computers can crank out new data all night long without&#10;human help, and the results may be offered for sale as information. They&#10;may or may not actually be so. Only a human being can recognize the&#10;meaning that separates information from data.&#10;&#10;In fact, information, in the economic sense of the word, consists of&#10;data which have been passed through a particular human mind and found&#10;meaningful within that mental context. One fella's information is all&#10;just data to someone else. If you're an anthropologist, my detailed&#10;charts of Tasaday kinship patterns might be critical information to you.&#10;If you're a banker from Hong Kong, they might barely seem to be data.">
    </outline>
    <outline text="Familiarity Has More Value than Scarcity." _note="With physical goods, there is a direct correlation between scarcity and&#10;value. Gold is more valuable than wheat, even though you can't eat it.&#10;While this is not always the case, the situation with information is&#10;often precisely the reverse. Most soft goods increase in value as they&#10;become more common. Familiarity is an important asset in the world of&#10;information. It may often be true that the best way to raise demand for&#10;your product is to give it away.&#10;&#10;While this has not always worked with shareware, it could be argued that&#10;there is a connection between the extent to which commercial software is&#10;pirated and the amount which gets sold. Broadly pirated software, such&#10;as Lotus 1-2-3 or WordPerfect, becomes a standard and benefits from Law&#10;of Increasing Returns based on familiarity.&#10;&#10;In regard to my own soft product, rock 'n' roll songs, there is no&#10;question that the band I write them for, the Grateful Dead, has&#10;increased its popularity enormously by giving them away. We have been&#10;letting people tape our concerts since the early seventies, but instead&#10;of reducing the demand for our product, we are now the largest concert&#10;draw in America, a fact that is at least in part attributable to the&#10;popularity generated by those tapes.&#10;&#10;True, I don't get any royalties on the millions of copies of my songs&#10;which have been extracted from concerts, but I see no reason to&#10;complain. The fact is, no one but the Grateful Dead can perform a&#10;Grateful Dead song, so if you want the experience and not its thin&#10;projection, you have to buy a ticket from us. In other words, our&#10;intellectual property protection derives from our being the only&#10;real-time source of it.">
    </outline>
    <outline text="Exclusivity Has Value." _note="The problem with a model that turns the physical scarcity/value ratio on&#10;its head is that sometimes the value of information is very much based&#10;on its scarcity. Exclusive possession of certain facts makes them more&#10;useful. If everyone knows about conditions which might drive a stock&#10;price up, the information is valueless.&#10;&#10;But again, the critical factor is usually time. It doesn't matter if&#10;this kind of information eventually becomes ubiquitous. What matters is&#10;being among the first who possess it and act on it. While potent secrets&#10;usually don't stay secret, they may remain so long enough to advance the&#10;cause of their original holders.">
    </outline>
    <outline text="Point of View and Authority Have Value." _note="In a world of floating realities and contradictory maps, rewards will&#10;accrue to those commentators whose maps seem to fit their territory&#10;snugly, based on their ability to yield predictable results for those&#10;who use them.&#10;&#10;In aesthetic information, whether poetry or rock 'n' roll, people are&#10;willing to buy the new product of an artist, sight-unseen, based on&#10;their having been delivered a pleasurable experience by previous work.&#10;&#10;Reality is an edit. People are willing to pay for the authority of those&#10;editors whose point of view seems to fit best. And again, point of view&#10;is an asset which cannot be stolen or duplicated. No one sees the world&#10;as Esther Dyson does, and the handsome fee she charges for her&#10;newsletter is actually payment for the privilege of looking at the world&#10;through her unique eyes.">
    </outline>
    <outline text="Time Replaces Space." _note="In the physical world, value depends heavily on possession or proximity&#10;in space. One owns the material that falls inside certain dimensional&#10;boundaries. The ability to act directly, exclusively, and as one wishes&#10;upon what falls inside those boundaries is the principal right of&#10;ownership. The relationship between value and scarcity is a limitation&#10;in space.&#10;&#10;In the virtual world, proximity in time is a value determinant. An&#10;informational product is generally more valuable the closer purchaser&#10;can place themselves to the moment of its expression, a limitation in&#10;time. Many kinds of information degrade rapidly with either time or&#10;reproduction. Relevance fades as the territory they map changes. Noise&#10;is introduced and bandwidth lost with passage away from the point where&#10;the information is first produced.&#10;&#10;Thus, listening to a Grateful Dead tape is hardly the same experience as&#10;attending a Grateful Dead concert. The closer one can get to the&#10;headwaters of an informational stream, the better one's chances of&#10;finding an accurate picture of reality in it. In an era of easy&#10;reproduction, the informational abstractions of popular experiences will&#10;propagate out from their source moments to reach anyone who's&#10;interested. But it's easy enough to restrict the real experience of the&#10;desirable event, whether knock-out punch or guitar lick, to those&#10;willing to pay for being there.">
    </outline>
    <outline text="The Protection of Execution" _note="In the hick town I come from, they don't give you much credit for just&#10;having ideas. You are judged by what you can make of them. As things&#10;continue to speed up, I think we see that execution is the best&#10;protection for those designs which become physical products. Or, as&#10;Steve Jobs once put it, &quot;Real artists ship.&quot; The big winner is usually&#10;the one who gets to the market first (and with enough organizational&#10;force to keep the lead).&#10;&#10;But, as we become fixated upon information commerce, many of us seem to&#10;think that originality alone is sufficient to convey value, deserving,&#10;with the right legal assurances, of a steady wage. In fact, the best way&#10;to protect intellectual property is to act on it. It's not enough to&#10;invent and patent; one has to innovate as well. Someone claims to have&#10;patented the microprocessor before Intel. Maybe so. If he'd actually&#10;started shipping microprocessors before Intel, his claim would seem far&#10;less spurious.">
    </outline>
    <outline text="Information as Its Own Reward" _note="It is now a commonplace to say that money is information. With the&#10;exception of Krugerrands, crumpled cab fare, and the contents of those&#10;suitcases that drug lords are reputed to carry, most of the money in the&#10;informatized world is in ones and zeros. The global money supply sloshes&#10;around the Net, as fluid as weather. It is also obvious, that&#10;information has become as fundamental to the creation of modern wealth&#10;as land and sunlight once were.&#10;&#10;What is less obvious is the extent to which information is acquiring&#10;intrinsic value, not as a means to acquisition but as the object to be&#10;acquired. I suppose this has always been less explicitly the case. In&#10;politics and academia, potency and information have always been closely&#10;related.&#10;&#10;However, as we increasingly buy information with money, we begin to see&#10;that buying information with other information is simple economic&#10;exchange without the necessity of converting the product into and out of&#10;currency. This is somewhat challenging for those who like clean&#10;accounting, since, information theory aside, informational exchange&#10;rates are too squishy to quantify to the decimal point.&#10;&#10;Nevertheless, most of what a middle-class American purchases has little&#10;to do with survival. We buy beauty, prestige, experience, education, and&#10;all the obscure pleasures of owning. Many of these things can not only&#10;be expressed in nonmaterial terms, they can be acquired by nonmaterial&#10;means.&#10;&#10;And then there are the inexplicable pleasures of information itself, the&#10;joys of learning, knowing, and teaching; the strange good feeling of&#10;information coming into and out of oneself. Playing with ideas is a&#10;recreation which people are willing to pay a lot for, given the market&#10;for books and elective seminars. We'd likely spend even more money for&#10;such pleasures if we didn't have so many opportunities to pay for ideas&#10;with other ideas. This explains much of the collective &quot;volunteer&quot; work&#10;which fills the archives, newsgroups, and databases of the Internet. Its&#10;denizens are not working for &quot;nothing,&quot; as is widely believed. Rather&#10;they are getting paid in something besides money. It is an economy which&#10;consists almost entirely of information.&#10;&#10;This may become the dominant form of human trade, and if we persist in&#10;modeling economics on a strictly monetary basis, we may be gravely&#10;misled.">
    </outline>
    <outline text="Getting Paid in Cyberspace" _note="How all the foregoing relates to solutions to the crisis in intellectual&#10;property is something I've barely started to wrap my mind around. It's&#10;fairly paradigm warping to look at information through fresh eyes - to&#10;see how very little it is like pig iron or pork bellies, and to imagine&#10;the tottering travesties of case law we will stack up if we go on&#10;legally treating it as though it were.&#10;&#10;As I've said, I believe these towers of outmoded boilerplate will be a&#10;smoking heap sometime in the next decade, and we mind miners will have&#10;no choice but to cast our lot with new systems that work.&#10;&#10;I'm not really so gloomy about our prospects as readers of this jeremiad&#10;so far might conclude. Solutions will emerge. Nature abhors a vacuum and&#10;so does commerce.&#10;&#10;Indeed, one of the aspects of the electronic frontier which I have&#10;always found most appealing - and the reason Mitch Kapor and I used that&#10;phrase in naming our foundation - is the degree to which it resembles&#10;the 19th-century American West in its natural preference for social&#10;devices that emerge from its conditions rather than those that are&#10;imposed from the outside.&#10;&#10;Until the West was fully settled and &quot;civilized&quot; in this century, order&#10;was established according to an unwritten Code of the West, which had&#10;the fluidity of common law rather than the rigidity of statutes. Ethics&#10;were more important than rules. Understandings were preferred over laws,&#10;which were, in any event, largely unenforceable.&#10;&#10;I believe that law, as we understand it, was developed to protect the&#10;interests which arose in the two economic &quot;waves&quot; which Alvin Toffler&#10;accurately identified in The Third Wave. The First Wave was&#10;agriculturally based and required law to order ownership of the&#10;principal source of production, land. In the Second Wave, manufacturing&#10;became the economic mainspring, and the structure of modern law grew&#10;around the centralized institutions that needed protection for their&#10;reserves of capital, labor, and hardware.&#10;&#10;Both of these economic systems required stability. Their laws were&#10;designed to resist change and to assure some equability of distribution&#10;within a fairly static social framework. The empty niches had to be&#10;constrained to preserve the predictability necessary to either land&#10;stewardship or capital formation.&#10;&#10;In the Third Wave we have now entered, information to a large extent&#10;replaces land, capital, and hardware, and information is most at home in&#10;a much more fluid and adaptable environment. The Third Wave is likely to&#10;bring a fundamental shift in the purposes and methods of law which will&#10;affect far more than simply those statutes which govern intellectual&#10;property.&#10;&#10;The &quot;terrain&quot; itself - the architecture of the Net - may come to serve&#10;many of the purposes which could only be maintained in the past by legal&#10;imposition. For example, it may be unnecessary to constitutionally&#10;assure freedom of expression in an environment which, in the words of my&#10;fellow EFF co-founder John Gilmore, &quot;treats censorship as a malfunction&quot;&#10;and reroutes proscribed ideas around it.&#10;&#10;Similar natural balancing mechanisms may arise to smooth over the social&#10;discontinuities which previously required legal intercession to set&#10;right. On the Net, these differences are more likely to be spanned by a&#10;continuous spectrum that connects as much as it separates.&#10;&#10;And, despite their fierce grip on the old legal structure, companies&#10;that trade in information are likely to find that their increasing&#10;inability to deal sensibly with technological issues will not be&#10;remedied in the courts, which won't be capable of producing verdicts&#10;predictable enough to be supportive of long-term enterprise. Every&#10;litigation will become like a game of Russian roulette, depending on the&#10;depth of the presiding judge's clue-impairment.&#10;&#10;Uncodified or adaptive &quot;law,&quot; while as &quot;fast, loose, and out of control&quot;&#10;as other emergent forms, is probably more likely to yield something like&#10;justice at this point. In fact, one can already see in development new&#10;practices to suit the conditions of virtual commerce. The life forms of&#10;information are evolving methods to protect their continued&#10;reproduction.&#10;&#10;For example, while all the tiny print on a commercial diskette envelope&#10;punctiliously requires a great deal of those who would open it, few who&#10;read those provisos follow them to the letter. And yet, the software&#10;business remains a very healthy sector of the American economy.&#10;&#10;Why is this? Because people seem to eventually buy the software they&#10;really use. Once a program becomes central to your work, you want the&#10;latest version of it, the best support, the actual manuals, all&#10;privileges attached to ownership. Such practical considerations will, in&#10;the absence of working law, become more and more important in getting&#10;paid for what might easily be obtained for nothing.&#10;&#10;I do think that some software is being purchased in the service of&#10;ethics or the abstract awareness that the failure to buy it will result&#10;in its not being produced any longer, but I'm going to leave those&#10;motivators aside. While I believe that the failure of law will almost&#10;certainly result in a compensating re-emergence of ethics as the&#10;ordering template of society, this is a belief I don't have room to&#10;support here.&#10;&#10;Instead, I think that, as in the case cited above, compensation for soft&#10;products will be driven primarily by practical considerations, all of&#10;them consistent with the true properties of digital information, where&#10;the value lies in it, and how it can be both manipulated and protected&#10;by technology.&#10;&#10;While the conundrum remains a conundrum, I can begin to see the&#10;directions from which solutions may emerge, based in part on broadening&#10;those practical solutions which are already in practice.">
    </outline>
    <outline text="Relationship and Its Tools" _note="I believe one idea is central to understanding liquid commerce:&#10;Information economics, in the absence of objects, will be based more on&#10;relationship than possession.&#10;&#10;One existing model for the future conveyance of intellectual property is&#10;real-time performance, a medium currently used only in theater, music,&#10;lectures, stand-up comedy, and pedagogy. I believe the concept of&#10;performance will expand to include most of the information economy, from&#10;multicasted soap operas to stock analysis. In these instances,&#10;commercial exchange will be more like ticket sales to a continuous show&#10;than the purchase of discrete bundles of that which is being shown.&#10;&#10;The other existing, model, of course, is service. The entire&#10;professional class - doctors, lawyers, consultants, architects, and so&#10;on - are already being paid directly for their intellectual property.&#10;Who needs copyright when you're on a retainer?&#10;&#10;In fact, until the late 18th century this model was applied to much of&#10;what is now copyrighted. Before the industrialization of creation,&#10;writers, composers, artists, and the like produced their products in the&#10;private service of patrons. Without objects to distribute in a mass&#10;market, creative people will return to a condition somewhat like this,&#10;except that they will serve many patrons, rather than one.&#10;&#10;We can already see the emergence of companies which base their existence&#10;on supporting and enhancing the soft property they create rather than&#10;selling it by the shrink-wrapped piece or embedding it in widgets.&#10;&#10;Trip Hawkins's new company for creating and licensing multimedia tools,&#10;3DO, is an example of what I'm talking about. 3DO doesn't intend to&#10;produce any commercial software or consumer devices. Instead, it will&#10;act as a kind of private standards setting body, mediating among&#10;software and device creators who will be their licensees. It will&#10;provide a point of commonality for relationships between a broad&#10;spectrum of entities.&#10;&#10;In any case, whether you think of yourself as a service provider or a&#10;performer, the future protection of your intellectual property will&#10;depend on your ability to control your relationship to the market - a&#10;relationship which will most likely live and grow over a period of time.&#10;&#10;The value of that relationship will reside in the quality of&#10;performance, the uniqueness of your point of view, the validity of your&#10;expertise, its relevance to your market, and, underlying everything, the&#10;ability of that market to access your creative services swiftly,&#10;conveniently, and interactively.">
    </outline>
    <outline text="Interaction and Protection" _note="Direct interaction will provide a lot of intellectual property&#10;protection in the future, and, indeed, already has. No one knows how&#10;many software pirates have bought legitimate copies of a program after&#10;calling its publisher for technical support and offering some proof of&#10;purchase, but I would guess the number is very high.&#10;&#10;The same kind of controls will be applicable to &quot;question and answer&quot;&#10;relationships between authorities (or artists) and those who seek their&#10;expertise. Newsletters, magazines, and books will be supplemented by the&#10;ability of their subscribers to ask direct questions of authors.&#10;&#10;Interactivity will be a billable commodity even in the absence of&#10;authorship. As people move into the Net and increasingly get their&#10;information directly from its point of production, unfiltered by&#10;centralized media, they will attempt to develop the same interactive&#10;ability to probe reality that only experience has provided them in the&#10;past. Live access to these distant &quot;eyes and ears&quot; will be much easier&#10;to cordon than access to static bundles of stored but easily&#10;reproducible information.&#10;&#10;In most cases, control will be based on restricting access to the&#10;freshest, highest bandwidth information. It will be a matter of defining&#10;the ticket, the venue, the performer, and the identity of the ticket&#10;holder, definitions which I believe will take their forms from&#10;technology, not law. In most cases, the defining technology will be&#10;cryptography.">
    </outline>
    <outline text="Crypto Bottling" _note="Cryptography, as I've said perhaps too many times, is the &quot;material&quot;&#10;from which the walls, boundaries - and bottles - of cyberspace will be&#10;fashioned.&#10;&#10;Of course there are problems with cryptography or any other purely&#10;technical method of property protection. It has always appeared to me&#10;that the more security you hide your goods behind, the more likely you&#10;are to turn your sanctuary into a target. Having come from a place where&#10;people leave their keys in their cars and don't even have keys to their&#10;houses, I remain convinced that the best obstacle to crime is a society&#10;with its ethics intact.&#10;&#10;While I admit that this is not the kind of society most of us live in, I&#10;also believe that a social over reliance on protection by barricades&#10;rather than conscience will eventually wither the latter by turning&#10;intrusion and theft into a sport, rather than a crime. This is already&#10;occurring in the digital domain as is evident in the activities of&#10;computer crackers.&#10;&#10;Furthermore, I would argue that initial efforts to protect digital&#10;copyright by copy protection contributed to the current condition in&#10;which most otherwise ethical computer users seem morally untroubled by&#10;their possession of pirated software.&#10;&#10;Instead of cultivating among the newly computerized a sense of respect&#10;for the work of their fellows, early reliance on copy protection led to&#10;the subliminal notion that cracking into a software package somehow&#10;&quot;earned&quot; one the right to use it. Limited not by conscience but by&#10;technical skill, many soon felt free to do whatever they could get away&#10;with. This will continue to be a potential liability of the encryption&#10;of digitized commerce.&#10;&#10;Furthermore, it's cautionary to remember that copy protection was&#10;rejected by the market in most areas. Many of the upcoming efforts to&#10;use cryptography-based protection schemes will probably suffer the same&#10;fate. People are not going to tolerate much that makes computers harder&#10;to use than they already are without any benefit to the user.&#10;&#10;Nevertheless, encryption has already demonstrated a certain blunt&#10;utility. New subscriptions to various commercial satellite TV services&#10;skyrocketed recently after their deployment of more robust encryption of&#10;their feeds. This, despite a booming backwoods trade in black decoder&#10;chips, conducted by folks who'd look more at home running moonshine than&#10;cracking code.&#10;&#10;Another obvious problem with encryption as a global solution is that&#10;once something has been unscrambled by a legitimate licensee, it may be&#10;available to massive reproduction.&#10;&#10;In some instances, reproduction following decryption may not be a&#10;problem. Many soft products degrade sharply in value with time. It may&#10;be that the only real interest in such products will be among those who&#10;have purchased the keys to immediacy.&#10;&#10;Furthermore, as software becomes more modular and distribution moves&#10;online, it will begin to metamorphose in direct interaction with its&#10;user base. Discontinuous upgrades will smooth into a constant process of&#10;incremental improvement and adaptation, some of it manmade and some of&#10;it arising through genetic algorithms. Pirated copies of software may&#10;become too static to have much value to anyone.&#10;&#10;Even in cases such as images, where the information is expected to&#10;remain fixed, the unencrypted file could still be interwoven with code&#10;which could continue to protect it by a wide variety of means.&#10;&#10;In most of the schemes I can project, the file would be &quot;alive&quot; with&#10;permanently embedded software that could &quot;sense&quot; the surrounding&#10;conditions and interact with them. For example, it might contain code&#10;that could detect the process of duplication and cause it to&#10;self-destruct.&#10;&#10;Other methods might give the file the ability to &quot;phone home&quot; through&#10;the Net to its original owner. The continued integrity of some files&#10;might require periodic &quot;feeding&quot; with digital cash from their host,&#10;which they would then relay back to their authors.&#10;&#10;Of course files that possess the independent ability to communicate&#10;upstream sound uncomfortably like the Morris Internet Worm. &quot;Live&quot; files&#10;do have a certain viral quality. And serious privacy issues would arise&#10;if everyone's computer were packed with digital spies.&#10;&#10;The point is that cryptography will enable protection technologies that&#10;will develop rapidly in the obsessive competition that has always&#10;existed between lock-makers and lock-breakers.&#10;&#10;But cryptography will not be used simply for making locks. It is also at&#10;the heart of both digital signatures and the aforementioned digital&#10;cash, both of which I believe will be central to the future protection&#10;of intellectual property.&#10;&#10;I believe that the generally acknowledged failure of the shareware model&#10;in software had less to do with dishonesty than with the simple&#10;inconvenience of paying for shareware. If the payment process can be&#10;automated, as digital cash and signature will make possible, I believe&#10;that soft product creators will reap a much higher return from the bread&#10;they cast upon the waters of cyberspace.&#10;&#10;Moreover, they will be spared much of the overhead presently attached to&#10;the marketing, manufacture, sales, and distribution of information&#10;products, whether those products are computer programs, books, CDs, or&#10;motion pictures. This will reduce prices and further increase the&#10;likelihood of noncompulsory payment.&#10;&#10;But of course there is a fundamental problem with a system that&#10;requires, through technology, payment for every access to a particular&#10;expression. It defeats the original Jeffersonian purpose of seeing that&#10;ideas were available to everyone regardless of their economic station. I&#10;am not comfortable with a model that will restrict inquiry to the&#10;wealthy.">
    </outline>
    <outline text="An Economy of Verbs" _note="The future forms and protections of intellectual property are densely&#10;obscured at this entrance to the Virtual Age. Nevertheless, I can make&#10;(or reiterate) a few flat statements that I earnestly believe won't look&#10;too silly in 50 years.&#10;&#10;-   In the absence of the old containers, almost everything we think we&#10;    know about intellectual property is wrong. We're going to have to&#10;    unlearn it. We're going to have to look at information as though&#10;    we'd never seen the stuff before.&#10;&#10;-   The protections that we will develop will rely far more on ethics&#10;    and technology than on law.&#10;&#10;-   Encryption will be the technical basis for most intellectual&#10;    property protection. (And should, for many reasons, be made more&#10;    widely available.)&#10;&#10;-   The economy of the future will be based on relationship rather than&#10;    possession. It will be continuous rather than sequential.&#10;&#10;-   And finally, in the years to come, most human exchange will be&#10;    virtual rather than physical, consisting not of stuff but the stuff&#10;    of which dreams are made. Our future business will be conducted in a&#10;    world made more of verbs than nouns.">
    </outline>
  </outline>
</outline>
  </body>
</opml>
